[SPEAKER_00]: Today's sutta is Samyutta Agama 636.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, I've heard, one time the Buddha was staying at Kukuttarama Monastery in the city of Pataliputra.
[SPEAKER_00]: At that time, the World Honored One addressed the beakers.
[SPEAKER_00]: I should explain to you the cultivation of the Four Establishments of Recollection.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the cultivation of the four establishments of recollection?
[SPEAKER_00]: And... the Buddha said...
[SPEAKER_00]: that when a tathāgata, an arahant, a perfectly awakened one, accomplished in knowledges and conduct, well gone, nowhere of the world, unsurpassed, guide of persons to be trained, teacher of the gods and humans, buddha, well-honored one, appears in the world, he proclaims the true dharma, excellent in the beginning, excellent in the middle, excellent in the end, good in the meaning and good in expression, pure and complete, revealing the brahmacharya, the holy life.
[SPEAKER_00]: A young man of good family or a young woman of good family, hearing the Dharma from the Buddha, gains pure faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having cultivated in this way, seeing the faults of the household life with its desires and pleasures, seeing the bondage of the defilements, they delight in solitary dwellings.
[SPEAKER_00]: They leave home to practice the path, no longer delighting in the household life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dwelling in homelessness, they aspire to complete purity and undertake the perfect and stainless brahmacharya for the whole life.
[SPEAKER_00]: They think, I would shave off hair and beard, put on the saffron robe and out of faith go forth from the household life into homelessness to practice the path.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having thought this, they abandon wealth and relatives, shave off their head and beard, put on saffron robe, out of faith go forth into homelessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: They straighten their bodily conduct, guard speech from the four faults, and purify their livelihood.
[SPEAKER_00]: They practice the noble precepts, guard the sense faculties, and protect the mind with right recollection.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the eye sees form, they do not grasp their general appearance, nor their particular features.
[SPEAKER_00]: If dwelling with the eye-faculty unrestrained, worldly desires and distress and unwholesome states flow into the mind, then they cultivate the proper discipline regarding the eye-faculty.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same way, they cultivate proper discipline regarding the ear, nose, tongue, body and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having perfected the noble precepts and well-guarded the sense-faculties,
[SPEAKER_00]: In going and coming, looking and turning, bending and stretching, in wearing robes, carrying the bowl, in eating, drinking, chewing, tasting, walking, standing, sitting, lying down, falling asleep and walking... twice... in speaking and remaining silent, they dwell clearly knowing and fully aware.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having perfected such noble precepts, guarding the sense faculties, possessing the right recollection and the right knowing, they dwell secluded and ease in solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: They sit alone in an empty place, at the root of a tree, or in a quiet dwelling.
[SPEAKER_00]: They straighten the body, establish the recollection before them, and compose the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: They abandon worldly desires and distress.
[SPEAKER_00]: Free from sensual desire, they purify the mind of sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: They abandon ill-will, sloth and torpor, restlessness and remorse, and doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Free from ill-will, sloth and torpor, restlessness and remorse, doubt, they purify the mind of these states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, they abandon the five hindrances that corrupt the mind, weaken the wisdom, obstruct progress and do not lead to nirvana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having abandoned these five hindrances, they dwell contemplating the body in the body, internally, ardent, clearly knowing, mindful, having subdued worldly desires and distress.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same way, they contemplate the body externally, internally and externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, likewise with feelings, with citta and dhammas, internally, externally, internally and externally, ardent, clearly knowing, recollected, having subdued worldly desires and distress.
[SPEAKER_00]: This bhikkhu is called the cultivation of the four establishments of recollection.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and when the Buddha has spoken thus, the bhikkhus rejoiced in his words.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, it's not like a long sutta and, obviously, you can see a certain
[SPEAKER_00]: amount of kind of parallels and similarity with the common Pali passages, such as, you know, gaining faith initially, on account of that, a person leaving the household life, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, what's interesting here, as we're going to see through, when we go through the questions I kind of asked, is that, well, the whole kind of four establishments of recollection, the satipaṭṭhānas,
[SPEAKER_00]: These are clearly described as a very kind of a encompassing process, so to speak, that pretty much starts by leaving the house of life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's far from a retreat technique that you could just adopt on top of your existing life values and behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the beginning of...
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, what is the cultivation of the four establishments of recollection?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's when Tathāgata arises in the world and a young man or a woman hear it and they gain faith in his teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is actually, I think, found in Pali.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like this explicitly, but it's in combination.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's some Anguttara Nikāya, shorter suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where it's said that pretty much there is no... it's not possible to see body as body internally, internally, externally, or both, if one is not living brahmacharya, withdrawn from worldly desires and afflictions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this sutta, in that regard, just kind of reiterates all those scattered statements throughout Pāli Nikaya.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, satipaṭṭhānas begin pretty much by
[SPEAKER_00]: Undertaking the training in virtue correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having cultivated this way, seeing the faults of the household life, in other words, what Pali sutras say, seeing that the household life is crowded, dusty, overwhelming, hard to maintain certain standards and training in that regard, because it's just the environment, it's not meant for it, that's why they would see the bondage and the defilements and start to delight in solitary dwellings and
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandoning it all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the... yeah, rather than being kind of going through the sutta technically and explaining the stuff that's self-evident, I thought of, well, discussing those kind of more like practical questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That a person, whether householder or a monk, can can still use, like today, to actually assess and re-evaluate and reflect on the practice at whatever stage they are in, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as I said, yeah, technically speaking, the observing body in the body and the satipaṭṭhānas are towards the end of the sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: After the whole training in virtue, sense restraint, abandoning the desires and the griefs of the world, but as I said, from a certain angle you could say, well, that's already the beginning of satipaṭṭhāna, because it all leads to the discernment of the citta, the body for what it is, not as a kind of compilation of
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, when you, like, read the sutta now, and you ask yourself, okay, so, what is mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_00]: When I, if I say mindfulness, mindfulness, what is mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sati.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's not even translate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's just say, what is sati?
[SPEAKER_00]: Ask yourself that question.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would you answer?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is sati?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, obviously, you'll give some... you might be giving some learned answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, sati is recollection, or it's this, and comes from the root of that word.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, like, for you, here and now,
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody were to ask you what is sati and you were to describe it, what phenomenon, palpable phenomenon, in your experience, here and now, would you be referring to?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when you say sati, what is the actual phenomenon that you are designating?
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you should be clear on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you might have, as I said, a semi-accurate idea of what sati is, on account of learning, and practice, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, when you say sati, even say, if you're not explaining it to anybody else, when you say, ah, sati, I should, I should practice mindfulness, what specific phenomenon are you referring to?
[SPEAKER_00]: What sums it up?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is its essence of the sati practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is it something that you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it like a technique that you go through a certain set of motions or verbal kind of cues that bring it up?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it something you just directly kind of, say, access, recollect, re-establish?
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way,
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it in and of itself?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is sati?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for you, how do you see it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's a useful thing to ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, and even if, by the way, if it feels clear, you should be checking in every now and then, because it might get obscured.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what tends to happen, practically speaking, is that, okay, you develop, as I said, some semi-accurate, more or less, doesn't matter, idea of sati,
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a kind of a summary of everything you learned, everything you tried, you know, a bit of right, a bit of wrong, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're operating under that imperative of I must be mindful and do this practice that kind of contains a certain degree of, as I said, moving complexity and moving parts of sati practice like this, in this scenario, doing this, body in the body...
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's like... but it's not seen as a single unifying phenomenon that reestablish everything correctly, pretty much instantaneously, when recollected or when put forward, whichever way you would choose to translate the Pārimukha from the different suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's important to dwell on this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you're not looking for a pleasingly theoretical, all-encompassing answer that would cover all angles.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're actually looking to see that phenomenon that you're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you say, yeah, mindfulness, or sati, or recollection, or recollectedness.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when I say that, what am I thinking of?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I see that clearly?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you start questioning that and then you'll see there's going to be a lot of layers to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's why it can be obviously very misleading as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I have no doubt that people without prior restraint and without simplification of their life, that this would list as a prerequisite to any practice of sati, they would still have some notion of sati.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like an entirely divorced concept that they cannot even fathom, unless they're celibate and practice, like... No, they can.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's whatever level of that phenomenon you can fathom, whatever idea you get, unless you're told that it won't be the sati you need to aim for, it will be the sati for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you won't be looking further.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will think, oh, that is the sati, because, again, it matches what the sutta says.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, it's recollection, embodying the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too difficult to wrap your head around these practices, but it's difficult to not fall into a trap whereby you stop recognizing or at least questioning whether there is more in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And obviously there is more in it, you know, if people start actually studying the whole body of the suttas and the āgamas and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: A clear picture emerges of, you know, how far you need to go and what you need to look for.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as I said before, most people would not necessarily undertake the level of that kind of study and practice, but it would more like be coming across the suttas here and there and second-hand accounts, and then very easily falling into the idea of, oh yeah, practice of mindfulness and recollection, I know what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they do know what it is at that time, to that extent, at that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if they were told to then also question it, like, oh, but is that it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it specifically that I'm referring to?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just, like, as I said, a combination of kind of semi-techniques, ideas, theories, a bit of, kind of, informed by some practical attempts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Specifically, when I say sati, what, what is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What state of mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: What attitude towards the mind I'm referring to?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in its kind of essence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without any secondary psychologizations, rationalizations, explanations or secondary cues.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's like a... once you start questioning it, and, as I said, you're going to start discovering layers and layers to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, one of the most obvious layers
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, when you start containing your worldly desires, not blindly following, and certainly not justifying them through your views,
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying, oh, there's no harm in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can handle it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you are, say, not able to give them up, you're at least on the level of views, maintaining the recognition that they're unbeneficial, obstructing, hindering and taking you away from the goal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you start training in that direction, start containing your desires, start practicing sensory strength, containing of the animal, well, that's when you recognize that whole new, real, so to speak, dimension of sati, that kind of brought into play, that didn't exist before.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, you cannot know or reference what doesn't exist for you in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's kind of the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like you need to be doing it to see that there is more to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And many suttas list those similes, many similes that explain exactly this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like... that's why the whole
[SPEAKER_00]: Brahmacharya, surmounting worldly, worldly desires, worldly worries, basically, entanglement with the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that, that needs to be the first point of practice of satipaṭṭhāna, of the Noble Eightfold Path or whatever, whichever way you want to designate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to begin by approximating the brahmacharya life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you're a householder or a monk that
[SPEAKER_00]: Training in virtue, sense restraint, guarding of the sense doors, subduing worldly desires and distress, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: the level of involvement, intentional involvement with the world, is the first step of satipaṭṭhāna, is how you practice it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, if your practice is not there yet, that you could sustain that type of lifestyle, well, you have work cut out for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Start working towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gradually, as I said, increasing saying no to the desires of the unwholesome, unbeneficial kind, until the mind will not be overwhelming you with panic, despair, anxiety, worry, at the mere thought of saying no to your central desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, as the other sutta says, like, initially, when a person not versed or trained in dhamma hears about sense restraint and saying no to their sensual and sexual desires, it feels like a sudden abyss, sudden precipice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, everything was fine and suddenly you just reach the cliff.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how quickly that dread arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's normal.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... that just shows you the state of the wilderness of that animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, okay, so instead of despairing on account of it or trying to, like, as I said...
[SPEAKER_00]: Rationalize it away through whatever views and stances and justifications.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take it on as a measure of what needs to be developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, when I think about sense restraint, when I think about approximating brahmacharya in a daily life and beginning the actual practice of satipaṭṭhāna correctly according to the suttas and āgamas, my animal freaks out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Citta just freaks out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's obviously too much too soon, but the direction remains outlined.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let me begin slowly building it up and making it sort of become used to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, the only reason it's a sudden precipice is because the whole direction has been ignored and pretended it doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why approximating brahmacharya in daily life doesn't mean like overnight you need to become perfectly celibate and meet all the requirements, but it means you need to start working towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bit by bit, wherever you are recognizing the excess, the unnecessity of your intentional, volitional,
[SPEAKER_00]: Engagement with centrality, proliferation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you start curbing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start saying no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start enduring bits and bits of those... of the... of the upsets and panics and little abysses that your animal will be coming up with until it calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, the only reason it feels so, like, powerful and overwhelming is because it's a new thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just hasn't been presented before and, obviously,
[SPEAKER_00]: Capturing a wild animal suddenly will obviously reveal how wild it is and how much it resists and hates it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eventually, it comes down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's kind of the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would be closer to practicing satipaṭṭhāna correctly by training in virtue and
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, by not doing that, or doing it conditionally with an expiry date for 10 days or 2 weeks or something, knowing that you would go back, and in the meantime do all these techniques of body scanning and whatnot, which has nothing, obviously, to do with the actual practice of satipaṭṭhāna that the suttas describe as the one way only that leads to purification.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so, I addressed that one, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so, like, there's a there's a thing that occurs a number of times in the sutta, and Pāli is as well mentioning.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, kind of, if I remember, Pāli mentions the equivalent of subduing worldly desires and distress.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think he mentions it as something that's already been done.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the Satipaṭṭhāna suttas, basically, or suttas that mention Satipaṭṭhāna, it was always mentioned as having dealt with that, having abandoned worldly joys and worries, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I forgot the common translation.
[SPEAKER_00]: He then dwells peaceful, withdrawn, here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: This āgama is kind of nice, because it includes a bit of a bit of nuance in between,
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereby, before a person is... a monk or a nun is dwelling happily in seclusion, purifying their mind from unwholesome states, they are making the effort subduing worldly desires and distress.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you trap the animal, the worldly desires, the desires of the prior, access to the wilderness and things they were causing you, joys, happiness, worry or distress, will keep coming up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you go about subduing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the question again.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be another reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: You ask yourself every now and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say you live withdrawn to the best extent you are able to at the time from unwholesome, unbeneficial desires and pursuits and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, you know, the untamed mind still comes up with pressures, desires, distress.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how are you subduing that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does it mean hypnotizing the mind to the point of no thoughts coming up?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's peaceful because it's asleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: But is that truly a peace?
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, take the simile of the wild animal that you're taming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does the real peace come when animal is just temporarily asleep?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or would the real peace come from when an animal is incapable of attacking you, regardless of whether it's awake, sleeping, agitated or not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is the actual, more foundational peace?
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, when the question is asked like that, you already know the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's kind of the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like that you shouldn't be trying to, like, well, calm down the animal, if it helps.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be doing it whether you want it or not, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you should certainly not fall into a view that artificially calming down the animal because it just scares me too much is the way of practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Teaching the animal, making it understand these things that you emulate through your own behavior and right choices by body, speech and mind, that is what will calm it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actual samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actual samatha.
[SPEAKER_00]: whereby, it doesn't matter what state the animal is in, because you know that it cannot turn against you, because it has been sufficiently tamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what the subduing of worldly desires and distress has to pertain to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when things concern with the world, desires and so on, yes, you say no to the outpours through your behavior, so you don't act out by body, by speech, by mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not where it ends.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like now you just spend time wishfully thinking that the animal will never remember again those things that used to, eh... spur desires in it, or distress.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, okay, so there is no acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've contained the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I actually have to, eh... reflect on these things correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bring them up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bring their counterparts up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Broaden the context, so when those thoughts do pop up, which they inevitably will,
[SPEAKER_00]: They won't limit the mind anymore, in the sense they used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: They won't be immediately called... inflict kind of narrowing of the focus of the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, they will be less and less of a trigger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's still the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still the same provocation, but comes with a different background.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that whole...
[SPEAKER_00]: I keep talking about, you know, the context, the broadening of the context, the right perceptions, bringing them up in a controlled, suitable, virtue-based environment, so that animal relearns to not just immediately fall for the trap, but not lose the sight of the broader picture, even when it's the most triggering things that come up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, another practical thing to consider would be, like, when the sutta talks about the faults of the household life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, now, there's a theoretical answer enumerating all the correct things, but more, like, for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and, by the way, again, it doesn't need to be household life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any current situation, you're gonna have a degree of
[SPEAKER_00]: Distraction, compromising choices, it's just like to what extent do I allow that... do you allow that to go?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, faults of household life could be faults of my current situation that are kind of self-inflicted, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you look for the moments where you're giving in to hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Comfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Forms of entertainment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, you're not judging or trying to get rid of the existence of those things or possibilities, but you're trying to see when your choice takes you there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you willingly choose to go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you willingly choose to give in to unnecessary excessive comfort or like food or entertainment, when you're delighting in socializing, even if it's on the basis of obligations, for example, I have to, but it's like, okay, but are you doing it because you have to or I have to becomes a permission for I can now carelessly engage with this because it has to be done and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you need to do is, as I say, keep an eye on your choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when the choice is clear, whether you're choosing that, you don't choose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do those things come up on their own and how often that becomes irrelevant?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the whole point is, like, you don't have to be fighting everything all the time, everything and nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to recognize when the choices are clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, again, they have to be clear, because whenever you are making a choice, means there is a consciousness of choosing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is the options that you are aware of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, the choice would be... making a choice would be incomprehensible, it would be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the choosing is that kind of a point of convergence, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you need to keep an eye on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the faults become faults.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where hindrances become hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you choose to take them up.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you choose to act out of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again,
[SPEAKER_00]: People keep choosing, not because they didn't have sufficient amount of special novelty hypnotic experiences in their meditation or revelations.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because they haven't really thought about this frequently enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: They haven't trained these reflections in order for them to sink in, to become, as I said, the informing context behind quick triggering desires, hindrances and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like, you know, so many suttas, like frequently recollecting and dwelling on the suitable themes, they would then be resulting in dispassion and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like a magical resolution, but it's just training and effort and diligence, really, nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it kind of ties in with the whole idea of guarding the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you don't have to be a monk or a nun in order to guard the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can already be doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you guard the sense doors?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you guard the sense doors after you chose to allow senses to look, smell, taste, touch unsuitable things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is guarding of the sense doors done before that?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, do you first give in to the unwholesome choice and then try to repair it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or are you able to not even give in to the unwholesome choice and then there is nothing to repair?
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, I already gave you an answer now, but the point is not the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is that you bring those questions to yourself as often as possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: That should be your meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, start painting the bigger picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bit by bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every time you start these reflections, you bring these questions that I keep sort of listing and creating, that revolve around the same things but give you different angles, you are adding to your canvas of that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are adding bit by bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: No masterpiece is painted overnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just like... but it grows.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It adds more.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you've been questioning before, part of it becomes, as I said, embedded in that context now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, next time you add more and more, and you don't have to keep revisiting everything from the start, because, as I said, it becomes part of that background that it's informing your current experience more and more accurately, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's pretty much how you will be developing the right view as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, say a person does this, practices questioning, then the whole place for seclusion... We spoke about it in other videos, so I won't go into too much detail on that here, but... Let me just... Just checking if the zoom is still on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the seclusion...
[SPEAKER_00]: To whatever extent you're able to have, say, periods of seclusion, re-evaluate... you should re-evaluate as to, like, can you improve it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, are there choices concerning my, you know, life, current living situation, duties and so on, that I could reorient, so to speak, so that I have more seclusion for practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, probably yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: For most people, especially in a household life, that could be improved.
[SPEAKER_00]: As for the monks, nuns, you realize, as I said, it can always be improved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not necessarily like you need to find a new place or something, but you would see that there is going to be at least some degree of your intentional involvements or engagements that would be taking you away from seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm just speaking broadly, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's up to every individual to assess that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because obviously, like, seclusion in and of itself, it's not gonna have magical results either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to be doing things rightly, practicing things rightly, where seclusion can then be the actual useful thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Re-evaluate at the end of your day.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there were no, say, extracurricular activities that you had to attend, monastery projects or, I don't know, family visits in a household life and stuff,
[SPEAKER_00]: Just reassess whether your choices are aligned with maximizing seclusion that you can get.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, not for sleeping or distracting yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for this, there's right practices, right reflections, right context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you spend that seclusion walking, hiking, sitting, studying the suttas, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be different times on different days.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, like, are you physically alone?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just you and your own mind, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: If a good part of your day, you could say, yeah, I mean, most of it is in seclusion, then you don't have to worry too much or micromanage, you know, every choice you make.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I shouldn't have talked about that, because, you know, five minutes longer or something, I could have had my... That's like, you know, becoming a bit precious and irrational about seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seclusion just means time when the work and reflection is most efficient.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, if you don't have seclusion, you can still do the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just won't be as efficient.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to recognize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like I can only practice when I'm in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there's no seclusion, there is no practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, householders became anāgāmīs in the sūtas, with their duties and families and things they had to look after.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously means they had to make more effort that would have been a lot more efficient if they were not householders, but the work is work, needs to be done and like, you know, I don't know, stuff can happen and you end up hospitalized or in an environment where you simply cannot practice seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: No amount of choices, right choices that you make.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you ready to practice in that environment?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is your idea of practice just completely, kind of, merged with seclusion?
[SPEAKER_00]: Without seclusion, it's just... there is no practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything I do, then, must be simply about bringing me back into seclusion, where I can practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not an accurate idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, seclusion is certainly a very, say, useful prerequisite, but it's a relative thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the obvious seclusion that physical seclusion would be leading to is seclusion from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seclusion from greed, aversion, distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you are not united with greed, aversion, distraction through presence of other bodies and people and sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're united through your own ignorant choices towards those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, physical seclusion can emulate the separation, but, as we already, I think, we did it in these studies as well, the actual seclusion, the only way to develop it, is from the inside, the withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's exactly how householders became anāgāmīs, like, overcome sensual desire, the five hindrances, the... sorry, the five lower fetters, while not being as secluded as monks, not even having an option to be so.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, they made the effort, applied the effort where it matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, internally, they have secluded themselves from the hindrances, from the unwholesome states, to the point of where certain views and assumptions in regard to centrality or will just were evaporated, were destroyed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that kind of ties in with the following point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is the practical ways of addressing the five hindrances correctly throughout the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you're secluded or not, as I said, seclusion is an added bonus, but if, whatever, things come up that prevent your seclusion, do you then justify your annoyance?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you feel righteous in your ill-will because somebody has interrupted your all-important seclusion?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you take that interruption of seclusion as the practice to not give in to the five hindrances?
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you have a choice what you're going to emphasize.
[SPEAKER_00]: The world, the concern with the world, which becomes seclusion, is another concern with the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the internal giving in to the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this instance would be irritation and ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, another kind of useful reference point, but again, I mean, I asked this, I added this to the end of the the self-questioning, because people can easily fall into technique of body watching and scanning.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's... say you are reflecting correctly, you are making
[SPEAKER_00]: The beneficial choices, saying no to the unbeneficial choices, containing the animal to the best of your ability.
[SPEAKER_00]: While you're doing that, which is, you could say, the meat of the practice, of the right practice, how often or are you simultaneous to whatever you're rightly practicing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you simultaneously aware with simply the state of your body as a whole, in your situation?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it seated?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it walking?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just like... do you see it as a... like, say, you're bringing up... like this now, where we spoke about seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're making sure you don't fall into a trap or becoming precious about seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're bringing up scenarios, you're reflecting, you're seeing if the animal becomes triggered on account of things it doesn't like.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, do you, like, allow it in a sense of, like, oh, yeah, yeah, and I should have done this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no, no, hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything, everything can be a basis for the right practice, if the right effort is made correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, while you're doing these reflections, do you also, in that whole package, so to speak, see yourself seated on a chair in your room, while thinking these things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, don't mystify too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: But don't completely exclude it either, those recognitions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, basically, those indirect ways... Should I tell you that now?
[SPEAKER_00]: It might just become another technique people seek.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anyway, I'm qualifying it now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, make sure it doesn't become another technique you seek.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, those indirect ways, when, say, you are
[SPEAKER_00]: Enduring things rightly, not giving in to sensuality, training in virtue, guarding of the sense doors, indirectly seeing your body in those situations, is the most accurate way of seeing the phenomenon of kāyā.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not when you're directly attending it, feeling it, or body scanning it and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, see, trying to directly attend to those indirect ways of the way the kāyā is recognized,
[SPEAKER_00]: You can start to emulate the indirect way, but it's actually rooted in your direct attention of gaining that mindfulness of the body or whatever you think it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way... well, the most accurate way of practicing mindfulness of the body is when it's genuinely, indirectly seen in regard to whatever, say, you are rightly preoccupied with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's training that indirect peripheral vision,
[SPEAKER_00]: And making sure that it doesn't become your, as I said, covertly, direct way of indirectly, peripherally seeing it, because you think it's a magical method for some purification.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Magical method for purification is making the right choices throughout your day.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is greed, non-greed, you choose non-greed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Aversion, non-aversion, you choose non-aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Distraction, non-distraction, you choose non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: By body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the best of your abilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more you do it,
[SPEAKER_00]: The clearer it will become what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the kind of last point is, is like, after, you know, everything we said, when you think, when you hear continuous, uninterrupted mindfulness, sati, that, you know, even the suttas mention,
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it mean to you?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you think that is?
[SPEAKER_00]: And I ask that because, again, like, despite everything we say, and even people that say, actually listen and think about these things, when you hear about continuous mindfulness, you still might think it's like, oh, it's like a continuous focus of non-interrupted pristine awareness of the pure consciousness of the eternal citta, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like this kind of full laser beam focus all the time, omniscient in every direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's like... is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, after everything you've said, the āgamas and these suttas and that suttas, and when we listed, you know, how satipaṭṭhāna is practiced, is that what continuous uninterrupted mindfulness would be?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or not?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, sit with that question.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the continuous uninterrupted mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it based on my determination to keep my focus aligned?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it an effortless result of doing things the right way, training the right way?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which one is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, obviously, I'm answering it because it's not about specific answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like asking yourself to see where your implications rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you still expect uninterrupted sati to be, as I said, like a uninterrupted beam of awareness that instantaneously sees everything all the time as it comes and it goes?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you think continuous mindfulness is basically where
[SPEAKER_00]: Emphasis cannot be reshifted back onto desire, ill-will, sloth, laziness, restlessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, those things will come up, but they don't shift the weight back onto them to become the center of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: They remain as something that has come up, but contained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that continuous mindfulness does not require you actively holding it together.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's obviously... you won't be mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's obviously narrowing of the perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's good to ask these things, because, like, you know, everybody, you're gonna have some preconceived notions hiding here and there, little expectations, that, as I said, will be fueling
[SPEAKER_00]: Certain expectations and modes of behavior that the only reason they do so, because you never really stopped and questioned them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, hold on, I'm still acting as if I'm supposed to be, you know, mindful, like, in every direction, omnisciently, all the time, in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that can't be the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: If mindfulness is developed on account of... Satipaṭṭhāna begins with training in virtue and sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that already is not something I'm doing all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm doing it when the choice to go that way or not presents itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm choosing rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm enduring the state of the animal that comes up as a result of that choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wait for it to calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: I present it with the right perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's like, oh, so that's really the mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that... an extent of the context has been developed sufficiently,
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereby, even without any effort from your part to bring the right context and contain the animal, the animal doesn't go back there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, the big picture that you painted now is clear as a day, and whatever pops in the front, the animal cannot not see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the uninterrupted, continuous mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the result of the... of building up the right practice.